<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A True and exact relation of the most remarkeable passages which haue happened in the Ile of Ree, commonly called Saint Martins Iland, since the 6. of August last past to the 24. of the same wherein is also declared, in what state our armie (vnder the command of the Duke of Buckingham his grace) is in, as also how it fareth with them of the fort, with the great hopes of the sudden surrender thereof, being driuen to great want both of victualls and water : together with the description of the seuerall workes, both offensiue and defensiue about the fort ... / written in French by a French gentleman of speciall accomps in the Ile of Ree, to a person of note here in England ; faithfully translated out of the French.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10503</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20779.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4441</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24402543</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24402543</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27640</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10503)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27640)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1824:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A True and exact relation of the most remarkeable passages which haue happened in the Ile of Ree, commonly called Saint Martins Iland, since the 6. of August last past to the 24. of the same wherein is also declared, in what state our armie (vnder the command of the Duke of Buckingham his grace) is in, as also how it fareth with them of the fort, with the great hopes of the sudden surrender thereof, being driuen to great want both of victualls and water : together with the description of the seuerall workes, both offensiue and defensiue about the fort ... / written in French by a French gentleman of speciall accomps in the Ile of Ree, to a person of note here in England ; faithfully translated out of the French.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nathaniell Butter dwelling neere S. Austines Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ré Island (France) --  History, Military.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  France --  1625-1649.</term>
               <term>France --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  1610-1643.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27640:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27640:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A True and Exact Relation of the moſt remarkeable paſſages which haue happened in the Ile of REE, commonly called <hi>Saint</hi> MARTINS <hi>Iland, ſince the</hi> 6. <hi>of Auguſt laſt paſt to the</hi> 24. <hi>of the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is alſo declared, in what ſtate our Armie (vnder the Command of the Duke of BVCKING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HAM his Grace) is in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As alſo how it fareth with them of the Fort, with the</hi> great hopes of the ſudden ſurrender thereof, being dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to great want both of victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls and water.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with</hi> The deſcription of the ſeuerall workes, both offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue and defenſiue about the Fort. The names of diuers Perſons of qualitie both ſlaine and hurt on the French ſide. The preſent ſtate of <hi>Rochell,</hi> and the borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring places about it. The willingneſſe of thoſe of the Religion to adhere to the D. of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of the French King to oppoſe them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written in French by a French Gentleman of ſpeciall accompt</hi> in the Ile of <hi>Ree,</hi> to a perſon of note here in England.</p>
            <p>Faithfully tranſlated out of the French.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Nathaniell Butter</hi> dwelling neere S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> Gate, 1627.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:27640:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27640:2"/>
            <head>A True and Exact Relation of the moſt remarkeable paſſages, <hi>which haue happened in the Jle of</hi> REE, commonly called Saint MARTINS <hi>Jland, ſince the</hi> 6. <hi>of Auguſt laſt past to the</hi> 24. <hi>of the ſame.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I doubt not but that you are informed of all that which hath paſt in this Iland of S. Martin, vntill this preſent time, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the good acquaintance which you haue at Court: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, I cannot leaue in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of your loue which you haue
<pb facs="tcp:27640:3"/>
expreſſed to me, to make you participant of all what is both here and in France paſt of late.</p>
            <p>They of Rochell hauing as it was differred as long poſſible vnto them to declare themſelues, intending to get great ſtore of Corne into their Citie, which they had about it, neuertheleſſe they finde themſelues now for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to doe it, by reaſon of the cruell and hard vſage of their enemies, which haue not ſuffered them to get one halfe of it into it, and are now come ſo cloſe to it, that hardly ſhall any man get any more into it by Land, for the Duke of Angoleine inquartered himſelfe on Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day laſt at Eſtre, with three thouſand foot, and a great number of horſe, which are diſperſed, beſides many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther foot throughout the Prouince of Rochell, which make there much ſpoile. The common Counſell of the ſaid Citie being thereupon aſſembled, they reſolued to ſend preſently for ayde to all their neighbours &amp; friends and at the ſame time they ſent ſome of their Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners to this Iland to craue my Lord Duke and Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Soubiſe</hi> to aſſiſt them ſpeedily with fiue hundred Frenchmen which wee had here, to aide them to raiſe vp againe the Fort of <hi>Taſdon,</hi> of which their enemies would make themſelues Maſters: and they were yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day promiſed, and ſent vnto them vnder the command of Monſieur <hi>de Loudriere.</hi> But there were ſome that before their departure would ſhew their valour by an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which Monſieur <hi>Sabignae Valouſo</hi> did vndertake, and executed their enterprize on the laſt Sunday about the euening, with fiue and twentie men. They of the Cittadell being brought to great extremities, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt round abound with trenches, which hinder them to get any refreſhments, did keepe with great care a pit in a halfe Moone, which furniſhed them euery day with
<pb facs="tcp:27640:3"/>
ſixe or ſeuen pipes of good water. The ſaid Monſieur <hi>de Sauignac</hi> went about eleuen of the clocke in the night time to aſſault the ſaid halfe Moone, and at the ſame time went three or foure ſouldiers of great reſolution to throwe ſome great bottles with Trane oyle into the ſaid pit, which they did, ſo that according to the relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a ſouldier of the Cittadell, who ſurrendred himſelfe yeſterday, the ſaid bottles being broken in pieces at the throwing in, the ſaid oyle hath infected and ſpoiled it, that hardly the water of it will bee good at any time to be vſed.</p>
            <p>If the ſaid Monſieur <hi>de Sauignac</hi> had not beene hurt. I beleeue that they ſhould haue taken the ſaid halfe Moone, for hee was hurt by a bullet of a piſtoll in his Groine, of which I hope that he ſhall ſhortly bee cured, and beſides himſelfe there were two of his wounded, but he and his ſlue eight or tenne of the Enemies, and a bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion of Engliſh which ſeconded our Frenchmen, loſt eight ſouldiers, and had betwixt twentie and thirtie hurt, amongſt which the Lieutenant of the Colonell <hi>Boroughs</hi> was one. In the ſame night did the Shalops of our Armie which waite euery night abroad, that none may goe in or out of the ſaid Cittadell, did take a Barque of tenne tunnes, which came to bring into it Bread, Wine, Meale, Peaſe, and Porke, beſides another Shalop, in which were ſeuen or eight men of note, and as many ſailers, which were carried by a wicked man of this Iland who is a Papiſt, both the Shalop and the men were drowned, except three, which were more happie then the other, hauing beene throwne into the Sea, and hurt in their heads with many musket ſhot. They being brought to the Land, I went at the dawning of the day on the border of the Sea, to ſee our Souldiers
<pb facs="tcp:27640:4"/>
imbarked, I did there a good turne to the ſaid Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, for I drew them out of the hands of the Souldiers, to make them to get lodging, and to bee cured by the Surgeons. Beſides the Conductors called Morriſiers and the Marriners, there were drowned theſe Gentlemen, Monſieur <hi>Artaignan,</hi> Cornet of the Companie of the Kings horſe which carrie little muskets, who was much beloued of his Maieſtie. Monſieur <hi>de la Tournelle,</hi> who was a Gentleman of the Duke of Bellegard. Monſieur <hi>du Clos,</hi> Lieutenant of Monſieur <hi>de Contamines,</hi> which was ſlaine at his landing, with two or three of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants. The names of them which are eſcaped are theſe which follow here: Monſieur <hi>de Iony</hi> Sonne of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of Breſt, Monſieur <hi>de Saint Michael</hi> Enſigne Colonell of the Regiment of Champaigne, and Monſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eur <hi>de Grandry</hi> Gentleman of the Duke of Bellegard, which came hither to get honour, and as we vnderſtood had promiſes of ſome places which might firſt fall voide. My Lord Duke and Monſieur <hi>Soubiſe</hi> viſited the ſaid Gentlemen on the ſame day they were landed.</p>
            <p>For to keepe a good order I ought to haue begunne with the murther, which hath beene intended againſt the perſon of my Lord Duke of Buckingham, which matter happened as followeth.</p>
            <p>A yong man of Blois being in the ſaid Cittadell du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſpace of two months, hee being a reſolute and couragious fellow, &amp; hearing many of the Propoſitions which were made amongſt the French, hee offered to fire one of the Ships of his Maieſtie of Great Britaine, if they would furniſh him with a Shalop and other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries for that purpoſe, yea he offered to fire the Ship in which my Lord came, and did ſtill lye in the night time as our enemies conceiued.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:27640:4"/>A certaine Captaine whoſe name is <hi>Caſtellan,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing this ſaid yong man to be ſo couragious and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, thinking him fit to performe a wicked deede, hee propounded vnto him, that if he would goe and murther my Lord Duke of Buckingham, that he could eaſily doe it by Land, and get a great reward, and an in compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble glorie.</p>
            <p>This fellow accepted to doe it, vpon condition that Monſieur <hi>Thorax</hi> (the Gouernour of the Citadell) would condiſcend to it; the ſaid Captaine aſſuring him of the conſent of Monſieur <hi>Thorax,</hi> the ſaid Souldier goeth in the night time out of the Citadell on the ſixt ot Auguſt, carying with him a very ſhort Dagger, but broad and of a good edge. But hee being perceiued and taken by our Horſe, he told vnto them that he came with an intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſerue on our ſide, which being not beleeued by them, ſeeing that he was of the Romiſh Religion, he was caried to Monſieur <hi>Soubeſe,</hi> and hee ſuſpecting him, ſent him as a Priſoner to the Prouoſt: Being there Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, hee perſiſted conſtantly in his firſt Tale: but at laſt when he was threatned to be Tortured, vnleſſe he would confeſſe the truth, hee begun to change his colour in his face, and grew very pale, and prayed that he might bee caried to my Lord of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> to make his Grace acquainted with matters of great importance: He being come to his Grace, he told him that which is here aboue reported, with diuers other circumſtances which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale here for ſome good reaſons, and hee was cauſed to ſet his hand to his depoſition. My Lo. Duke ſent word the next day to Monſieur <hi>Thorax</hi> in the Citadell, and gaue him to vnderſtand, that if he would ſend vnto him three or foure of them of his Garriſon, in which hee put
<pb facs="tcp:27640:5"/>
moſt truſt, that they ſhould come ſafely, and that hee would make them to ſee ſomething, which hee deſired they ſhould communicate afterwards vnto him: The Gouernour ſent thereupon preſently ſixe of h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s moſt tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted friends, and amongſt the reſt the Barron of S. Surie: But the aboue mentioned matter being ſhewed vnto them, they denied it flatly, and the Priſoner maintained it againſt them, and thereupon returning to the Citadel, ſome that miſtruſted the matter, murmured againſt the Gouernour, and others which thought well of him, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended his credit and honour.</p>
            <p>They hauing made this report vnto the Gouernour, he proteſted that hee was innocent in the ſaid matter, and ſent againe after dinner to our Campe, both his owne Brother and Baron of Surin, beſides the Captaine <hi>Castellan,</hi> which laboured there both with faire ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and great oathes to take away this ill opinion and conceit of the Gouernour, as they termed it. But the Priſoner perſiſted ſtill in his former ſaying, and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his depoſition as before.</p>
            <p>They requiring thereupon that hee ſhould bee put to the torture, ours laught at it, ſaying, that it is but giuen to them which deny a crime, and not to ſuch as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:27640:5"/>They intreated thereupon that wee would put him to death, with a proteſtation, that in caſe hee did not recall his ſaying before his death, that they all there would in ſuch caſe ſuffer themſelues to be hanged after him, &amp; that if it were required, they would yet cauſe tenne other to come, that ſhould ſtand to the like condition.</p>
            <p>Their offer was at that time refuſed: but my Lo: Duke ſent them word the next day, that he would cauſe the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable wretch to be put to death, if they would ſend him the ſaid <hi>Caſtellan,</hi> vpon condition that he might doe with him what he ſhould be pleaſed to doe, if the ſaid priſoner ſhould not recall his depoſition before his death, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in his accuſation, and that hee would giue way that they ſhould giue him ſuch a Confeſſor as they ſhould like beſt: beſides tenne of their Gentlemen which ſhould be witneſſes of that which ſhould paſſe.</p>
            <p>But they of the Citadell refuſed to ſend the ſaid <hi>Caſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan,</hi> alledging that he was there very neceſſary for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the King: whereby it happened that many which doubted of the matter the day before, did then firmly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it.</p>
            <p>I did not thinke in the beginning to extend my ſelfe ſo largely in the relation of the particulars of the aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned matter, but many are ſomtimes glad to learne the circumſtances of a buſineſſe or accident, to iudge the better of the matter.</p>
            <p>I beleeue that if they can ſend Letters from the Court of <hi>France</hi> to that of <hi>England</hi> (as they report here, that there is good paſſage) that they will doe their beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours to make you there to beleeue many idle and friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous tales. But concerning mee you ſhall haue nothing from mee but truth according to mine owne vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and knowledge.</p>
            <p>My Lord Duke knoweth now very well their deuices, and laughes them out ſometimes with much grace, when hee ſpeaketh to any of the enemies of their great force
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:27640:6"/>
both by water, and by land, of their vndoubtfull ſuccour, and of their imaginary armies in diuers parts of <hi>France,</hi> which ſhould amount according to their calculation to more then 50000 men, which are now come to eight or nine thouſand, for the moſt: And although they were ſo ſtrong as they report, they were not able to hinder vs of the taking of this Cittadell and that within the ſpace of fifteene dayes, or three weekes.</p>
            <p>The common ſouldiers which are in it haue now but one bisket in a day, and once water, and the Gentlemen and Captaines haue not much more. It is true that this retardment is troubleſome, and not onely hindered our deſignes, but maketh them likewiſe more difficult to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and ſhall therefore be more glorious if wee atchieue them. I thinke that there ſhall be a good occaſion giuen to vs in theſe parts; for almoſt all the forces of the French King march towards <hi>Rochel,</hi> and there are already foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene Companies of the Regiment of the Gardes, beſides many Swiſſers, and a great deale of ordnance. Many are reſolued to ſuccour them, although the paſſages are well ſtopt. They haue ſeized vpon the perſon of Monſ. <hi>de Beaulieu d'Ampierre</hi> in his owne houſe, fearing that hee ſhould moleſt them, as he hath done in the former wars. We haue already meanes to make them to reſtore him vnto vs, and we hope ſhortly to haue more. We are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified that the Duke of <hi>Rohan</hi> is very ſtrong in the field, and that he intendeth to goe to <hi>Montauban</hi> on the 25 of this moneth. Seeing that the City of <hi>Rochel</hi> hath now in a manner declared it ſelfe, I doubt not but that all the reſt of the Religion which are in France which before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to learne what they ſhould doe, will ſhortly make ſome attempt.</p>
            <p>Here are lately ſome ariued from <hi>Rochel,</hi> which report that our ſouldiers are there happily ariued, and receiued with great ioy. It is true, that their little delay hath made them to gather great ſtore of good prouiſion, by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27640:6"/>
which the City is furniſhed for the ſpace of a yeare, or more. And in this Iland there ſhall be wine enough ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, notwithſtanding the waſtes and ſpoile which the ſouldiers and Mariners haue made. We are likewiſe aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that this night there haue beene ſunke three Shalops which were comming to the ſaid Citadell, which ſhall make them to loſe all deſire to venture any more in ſuch a manner. This is all moſt-what we haue of any importance at this preſent time.</p>
            <p>For to trouble vs with other particulars of no moment, it is not needfull, namely concerning them which haue either beene ſlaine or hurt of both ſides, as in the ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contres, ſkirmiſhes, and with the Cannon ſhot and caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of granads, and other things of leſſer importance, which would require a whole volume to write them all together downe.</p>
            <p>Now at this inſtant are here ariued ſome Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of <hi>Rochel</hi> which are come to conferre with my Lord Duke and Monſ. <hi>de Soubiſe,</hi> to make him acquainted with that which is Saturday laſt paſt betwixt them and the D. of <hi>Angouleſme,</hi> who hath made faire offers vnto them, and did yeſterday ſend into the ſaid City Monſ. <hi>de Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minges,</hi> who commandeth the Fort which is called <hi>Lewis,</hi> proteſting that if they will cauſe the Engliſh to remoue, that good contentment ſhall be giuen to them, and all the Proteſtants of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At <hi>S. Martena</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Ré</hi> the 26 of Auguſt, 1627 new ſtile.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:27640:7"/>This ſame day, 17 of <hi>Auguſt Monſ. de Briſſac</hi> a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of the Religion is come out of the Citadell, with ſome other Gentlemen, to retire home with the permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my <hi>Lord Duke</hi> and of <hi>Monſ. de Soubize.</hi> They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that in the Citadell they ſuffer great incommodities, but they thinke they may yet keepe it a whole moneth, or thereabout. Eight Souldiers which haue fled out of it, &amp; are come to vs, affirme that they are at their laſt breath. My <hi>Lord Duke</hi> is loued and admired of all men for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great and excellent parts which are in him.</p>
            <p>SIR I ſent you eight dayes agoe a little packet, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing now occaſion to acquaint you with more newes, I will impart vnto you ſuch as I haue at this preſent. Since that time we haue not receiued any other but good newes.</p>
            <p>They of <hi>Rochel</hi> haue begun to make their workes out of the gate of <hi>S. Nicholas</hi> neere which lyeth their Fort of <hi>Tadon</hi> to hinder the aproaches of their Enemies inquar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering. Although they haue not as yet made any open declarations, they gouerne themſelues neuertheleſſe as if were ioyned. The <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>chiefeſt Papiſts</hi> haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy forſaken the ſaid Citie, and there come daily ſome ſouldiers in it, which are there well receiued and lodged. A declaration of the <hi>French King</hi> being lately ſent vnto them, which forbiddeth very ſtrictly to adhere or ioyne with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> they would not publiſh it, knowing ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, that vnleſſe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſuccour had come, there was a reſolution taken to ſubdue them this Summer. Wee expect here ſhortly 5000 men from <hi>England,</hi> and if they come, we will vndertake ſome other enterpriſes then the taking of the Citadell, which is now at the laſt gaſp, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that they expect ſuccour from <hi>Marans</hi> both of men and victuals within the ſpace of two daies, as they ſay. Their Enſigne of the Colonell, of which I made mention in my former, hath by reaſon of the negligence
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:27640:7"/>
of his keepers, three dayes agoe made an eſcape. His Companions were caryed to the Shipps board by good fortune: for they were all three as a recompence giuen to that braue <hi>Engliſh Captaine,</hi> who was hurt with <hi>Mounſ-Savignac.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We haue foure dayes agoe ſent into the Citadell all the women and children of thoſe of this Borough, which are in the Citadell, which were retreated into it, in lieu of ſo many Gentlemen and Souldiers, which haue forſaken it, but they may ſerue them to dreſſe their meate, for they haue lately killed and ſalted the remnant of their horſes. They of the Fort are now ſo enuironed with our tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that a dogge cannot come into it.</p>
            <p>There ſhall now an offer be made vnto them to ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themſelues within the ſpace of a few dayes, and after the expiration of them there ſhall no compoſition bee made with them as it is here reported.</p>
            <p>For thoſe which are in the Fort <hi>de la Pree,</hi> they are ſo little regarded, that wee aſſault them not, but kill and take them onely when they come abroad, and dare goe into the next villages for refreſhments.</p>
            <p>This is almoſt all the matter of importance which I had now to write. All the newes which come from <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> are much to be ſuſpected. Both there and in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>France</hi> there are rumors ſpread abroad of Maſſacres againſt the Proteſtants, I pray God to preſerue them. It is likewiſe reported that the <hi>French King</hi> is to come in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to beſiege <hi>Rochel</hi> with 40000 men: But if the 30000 men ſhall timely come, which the Proteſtants expect, they will finde them worke enough.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Soubize</hi> hath lately receiued very good newes from <hi>Languedock</hi> and other places, the particulars whereof are not yet come to my notice. At the next occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I ſhall acquaint you with them, and of ſuch things as ſhall fall out from time to time.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:27640:8"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From the Iland of S. Martin <date>the 24 of Auguſt, 1627 new ſtile. To vs the 14.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>I Haue heard now newes of Capt. <hi>Gifford</hi> ſince I came from <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> where I parted from him when hee was ready to goe on boord his ſhip. I enquired for him af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the battell, but he was not landed, neither is his ſhip yet come into the Fleet. I pray God it be not caſt away. You may let my Godfather know this, but none elſe. I pray remember my duty to him.</p>
               <p>Capt. <hi>Talbot</hi> is not ſlaine, therefore put out his name from among the dead. Sir <hi>George Blundel</hi> dyed at <hi>Rochel</hi> of the wounds he receiued in the ſight.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Charles Rich</hi> was ſhot in the ſhouldier, but there is no danger of death by it. It is reported confidently at <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> that we loſt 3000 men at our landing, and the French but 70. I haue ſcaped many dangers ſince I par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from you, I thanke God, both by ſea and land.</p>
               <p>The enemy playes vpon the Towne wherein wee are continually with his ordnance from the Cittadell, which is leſſe then musket ſhot from the Towne, and wee play vpon the Cittadell, hauing three batteries by land, and one by ſea.</p>
               <p>I haue eſcaped narrowly from being ſlaine by the ſhot both of the Cannon and Musket, and diuers other wayes, I thank God, I hope he hath reſerued me for a better end, and I pray heartily he would preſerue mee from ſudden death.</p>
               <p>My lord Duke hath gained a great deale of honour in this imployment, and is ſometime blamed for hazarding ſo much his owne perſon. Our houſe wherein he lodgeth hath beene twice ſhot through, and his Barge-roome ſhot through and through.</p>
               <p>We tooke one that was incouraged by Monſ. <hi>de Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rax,</hi> and others in the Cittadell to kill our Generall: hee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:27640:8"/>
had about him a ſhort Poniard, and did confeſſe that hee was reſolued by that or ſome other way to kil my L. Duke within a fortnight.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <opener>
                  <dateline>From Pindennis Caſtle in Famouth, <date>Aug. 21.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>Wee haue receiued newes from the D. that Sir <hi>Ralph Shelton</hi> by killing a braue Monſieur hand to hand in fight of both the armies, is made a Lieutenant Colonell to Sir <hi>I. Radliffe,</hi> who is made Colonell.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
